Guide to the Lucy Maynard Salmon Papers, 1818-1992 (bulk 1854-1933)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
- SERIES VII. VASSAR COLLEGE
  - History Department
    - Course outlines and examinations: Miscellaneous (Folder 59.21)
    - Examples of Vassar College student work in history (Folder 59.22)
    - Methods of Teaching (Folder 59.23)
    - Course descriptions, 1904-1910; (5 items) (Folder 31.6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1917-1925; (10 items) (Folder 31.7)
  - Publications
    - Vassar College Bulletin - volume XVII, no. 2, Sept 1927 (Folder 32.1)
    - Vassar College Bulletin - volume XVII, no. 3, October 1927 (Folder 32.2)
    - Vassar Quarterly (includes article about Lucy Maynard Salmon), May 1930 (Folder 32.3)
    - Vassar Quarterly (includes article on LMS Fund For Research), February 1932 (Folder 32.4)
    - The Vassar Miscellany News, 1921-1927; (12 issues) (Folder 32.5)
- SERIES VIII. RESEARCH AND SUBJECT FILES
  - History and Teaching
    - Proceedings of the Association of History Teachers... - no. 25, 1927 (Folder 32.7)
    - Middle States Association of History Proceedings - no. 31, 1933 (Folder 32.8)
    - Influence on the teaching of history. Includes notes by Lucy Maynard Salmon and a collection of correspondence arranged chronologically, 1890-1926 (Folder 48.1)
    - American Historical Association. Committee of Seven (Teaching history in secondary schools and colleges), Europe. Includes clippings, notes on itinerary, address book, letters of introduction, letters from Charles Homer Haskins, Williston Hough, Michael Ernest Sadler, Charles Seignobos, and Andrew D. White; also a statement of household expenses in London, 1898. (See also 47.1-.3: Trips to Europe.), 1897, 1898-1900 (Folder 48.2)
    - Proposed book on History in the Schools. Four letters from Nicholas Murray Butler, 1898, and 2 letters and an agreement with the Macmillan Co., 1898-1899 (Folder 48.3)
    - A collection of pamphlets on the teaching of history, 1863-1909 (Folder 48.4)
    - College entrance requirements for history. Includes copy of an article by Lucy Maynard Salmon published in The Academy, May 1888; a typescript, "Discussion of Professor H. Morse Stephens' Paper 'Shall Historical Studies Be a Necessary Part of College Entrance Requirements?'", 1896; correspondence regarding it, including letters from James R. Rhoads and Moses Coit Tyler; later letters from Mary G. Barnes, William MacDonald, and Adam Leroy Jones; a statement of principles; and clippings. (Folder 48.5)
    - Association of History Teachers of the Middle States and Maryland. Lucy Maynard Salmon was the first president of the organization; the folder includes historical information, programs, and correspondence, 1897-1933 (Folder 48.6)
    - New York City Board of Education examination for teachers. A letter from William Maxwell, Superintendent, 1901, and information about license requirements. Report of the Public Education Association, 1900. (Folder 48.7)
    - History Teacher's Magazine. A letter from James Franklin Jameson and letters from the editor, Albert E. McKinley. (Folder 48.8)
    - Democracy in Education. Includes a manuscript by Lucy Maynard Salmon. (Folder 48.9)
    - Women’s Education. Includes correspondence, with a copy of one reply by Lucy Maynard Salmon; and clippings. (Folder 48.10)
    - Western Association of Collegiate Alumnae. Information about organization and correspondence, 1884-1926 (Folder 48.11)
    - Association of Collegiate Alumnae. Data about organization. (Folder 48.12)
    - Association of Collegiate Alumnae. Correspondence, including letters from Herbert B. Adams, Alice Freeman Palmer, Marion Talbot, and M. Carey Thomas, 1885-1912 (Folder 48.13)
    - American Association of University Women. Lucy Maynard Salmon certificate of life membership and information about the organization. (Folder 48.14)
    - Association of Colleges and Preparatory Schools of the Middle States and Maryland. Includes article by Lucy Maynard Salmon, "The Encroachments of the Secondary Schools on the College Curriculum" (1906), and a convention program in which she participated (1902). (Folder 48.15)
    - American Association of University Professors. Information about the organization, reports, and correspondence, 1915-1921 (Folders 48.16 - 48.17)
    - International Historical Congress, The Hague, 1898 (Folder 48.18)
    - Academic freedom. Mounted newspaper clippings and articles, 1901-1917 (Folders 48.19 - 48.21)
    - Articles and clippings relating to college and university organization, trustees, curriculum. (Folder 48.22)
    - Education in England — Collection of documents and pamphlets relating to education, circa 1889-1904 (Folder 48.23)
    - Education in France — Collection of documents and pamphlets relating to education, circa 1889-1904 (Folders 48.24 - 48.25)
    - Collection of documents and pamphlets relating to education: Italy, circa 1889-1904 (Folder 47.41)
    - Education in the South. Includes correspondence and publications relating to Lucy Maynard Salmon teaching in the Summer School of the South, University of Tennessee, 1906 (Folder 47.39)
    - Old South Historical Work. Miscellaneous publications and lecture announcements. (Folder 47.40)
    - Senate school bill — for the foundation of a state school at Delhi, NY, 4 Feb 1908; (5 pages) (Folder 37.14)
    - Wilcox, Alice Wilson (VC 1894). Outline of Rhode Island Historical Associations, Landmarks and Documents, 1897; (11 pages) (Folder 35.10)
  - Domestic Service
    - Interest in home economics. General. Includes announcements of lectures, correspondence 1888-1916, reports, and clippings. (Folders 49.3 - 49.3A)
    - Domestic service correspondence. Replies to a questionnaire sent out by the Vassar History Department, 1888-1890, including a copy of the questionnaire, correspondence with John B. Clark and Richard T. Ely relating to it; and charts tabulating information for towns throughout the country. (Folders 49.4 - 49.6)
    - Press notices of lectures and articles on domestic service, 1891-1893, and letters from Ellen Battelle Dietrick (?), 1889, and Florence Kelley, 1901. (Folder 49.7)
    - Domestic Service, NY: Macmillan, 1897 (2d ed. 1901). Correspondence with Macmillan Co., including contract, review, criticisms, sales, and a box of clippings. Includes letters from Elizabeth Converse and Marion Talbot. (Folder 49.8-.8A)
    - Correspondence with W.D.P. Bliss relating to article on "Domestic Service" for the Encyclopedia of Social Reform, 1906-1907 (Folder 49.9)
    - Household Research. Includes reports and copies of the bulletin of the Intermunicipal Committee on Household Research, and information and correspondence about the New York Association for Household Research. (Folder 49.10)
    - Progress in the Household (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1906). Correspondence and reviews. (Folder 49.11)
    - Miscellaneous notes and clippings relating to domestic service. (Folder 49.12)
    - Domestic service in Germany. Lucy Maynard Salmon notes. (Folder 49.13)
    - Knitting controversy (World War I). Clippings. (Folder 49.14)
    - Clippings Box, labeled box 10, stored in back of folders in box 49 (Box 49)
    - Publications relating to domestic service, including a "Bibliography of Domestic Economy" ( State Library Bulletin, Bibliography no. 22, June 1990, University of the State of New York). (Box 50)
    - Women's Educational and Industrial Union Reports, 1888 - 1890 (Box 51)
    - Announcements and reports of Woman's Work Exchanges, 1885 - 1890 (Box 52)
    - Announcements and reports of Women’s Work Exchanges (including U.S. and Germany), 1890 - 1902 (Box 53)
    - Letters and clippings from Angelina Blackinton Sturgis Thurber to Mrs. J. Manchester Haynes concerning domestic service, 1891-1892; (3 letters, 2 clippings) (Folder 65.1)
  - Laundry Lists
    - Analysis of laundry lists (Folder 54.1)
    - News clippings regarding Lucy Salmon and laundry and other articles referring to laundry (Folder 54.2)
    - Correspondence to and from laundry establishments regarding the acquisition of laundry lists (Folder 54.3)
    - Laundry Tags (Folder 54.4)
    - Laundry Advertisements (Folder 54.5)
    - Foreign Laundry Lists (Folders 54.6 - 54.7)
    - East Central States laundry lists (Folder 54.8)
    - Middle Western States laundry lists (Folder 54.9)
    - New England laundry lists (Folder 54.10)
    - New York City laundry lists (Folders 55.1 - 55.3)
    - New York State laundry lists (Folders 55.4 - 55.5)
    - Southern States laundry lists (Folder 55.6)
    - United States laundry lists (Folder 55.7)
    - United States laundry lists (Folder 55.8)
    - Western States laundry lists (Folders 56.1 - 56.4)
    - Unsorted laundry lists (Folders 56.5 - 56.8)
    - Duplicate laundry lists (Folder 56.9)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Interest in the newspaper field. General. A file of correspondence, 1915-1927, including a letter about Lucy Maynard Salmon article on "Censorship" in the 13th edition of the Encylopaedia Britannica, 1926, and bibliographies. (Folder 57.1)
    - Correspondence and material re: The Ulster County Gazette (Folder 57.2)
    - Correspondence regarding The Newspaper and Authority, N.Y.: Oxford, 1923; The Newspaper and the Historian, NY: Oxford, 1923; and "The Newspaper and Research," American Journal of Sociology, XXXII, pp. 217-218 (September 1926). (Folder 57.3)
    - Reviews and clippings regarding the preceding publications. (Folder 57.4)
    - American Civic Association. Correspondence, 1910-1916, leaflets, and also a publication of the Massachusetts Civic League. (Folder 57.5)
    - Civil Liberties. Correspondence with the American Civil Liberties Union, and NY Assembly correspondence relating to the Lusk bills(1920). (Folder 57.6)
    - Civil Service Reform. Announcements of programs including Lucy Maynard Salmon; correspondence, 1901-1909; and publications. (Folders 57.7 - 57.8)
    - Correspondence and clippings regarding History of the Appointing Power of the President, American Historical Association, 1886, and the Macmillan contract for a revised edition, 1901. (Folder 57.9)
    - Interest in civic welfare, Poughkeepsie. Correspondence, 1907-1916, leaflets, 5 manuscript items, notes, contributions to newspapers (1923) urging support for the local library, and clippings. (Folder 57.10)
    - Collection of mounted clippings relating to Commission government in Poughkeepsie, 1918 (Folder 57.11)
    - Woman Suffrage. Includes Lucy Maynard Salmon manuscript; correspondence including letters from Harriot Stanton Blatch, Carrie Chapman Catt, Alice Paul, Anna Howard Shaw, Doris Stevens, and M. Carey Thomas; clippings (Folder 57.12)
    - Woman Suffrage. Certificate of membership as an honorary regent of the Volunteer League of the National American Woman Suffrage Association. (Folder 57.12A)
    - Clippings related to women, 1906-1916 (Folder 57.13)
    - American Historical Association. Information on organization, programs, and correspondence, 1885-1921 (Folder 57.14)
    - Daughters of the American Revolution and National Society of Colonial Dames. Programs, yearbooks, and clippings. (Folder 57.15)
    - New York State Historical Association. Invitation to deliver annual address, 1905 (Folder 57.16)
    - Hall of Fame Elector. Constitution; rules for elections; and correspondence, 1905-1920 (Folder 57.17)
    - The Searchlight. 3 letters regarding subscription and financial difficulties, 1920-1921 (Folder 57.18)
    - Notes and ephemera concerning the 1904 presidential election (Folder 57.26)
    - "List of References Relative to New York Manors," prepared by Victor H. Paltsits, 4 Apr 1908 (Folder 57.27)
- SERIES IX. MARIA CLARA MAYNARD PAPERS
  - Biography
    - Diaries of Maria Clara Maynard, 1840; (2 volumes) (Folder 36.2)
    - Diary of Maria Clara Maynard Salmon, 1862-1863; (1 volume) (Folder 36.3)
    - Diary of Maria Clara Maynard, 1862-1863; (11 pages, TS) (Folder 36.4)
    - Financial records of Maria Clara Maynard Salmon, undated; (1 volume) (Folder 36.5)
    - Ipswich Female Seminary, 1831-1839; (2 catalogues) (Folder 30.2)
  - Education
    - Class notes, circa 1834; (6 notebooks) (Folder 34.1)
    - Class notes, circa 1834; (3 notebooks) (Folder 34.2)
    - Class notes, circa 1834; (2 notebooks) (Folder 34.3)
    - Recipe book, undated; (1 volume) (Folder 36.6)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 38.15)
  - Letters from Maria Clara Maynard Salmon
    - Belden, Miranda Smith, 1838-1839; (10 letters) (Folder 26.1)
    - Belden, Miranda Smith, 1840-1844; (13 letters) (Folder 26.2)
    - Burnham-Wolcott, 1838-1852; (8 letters) (Folder 26.6)
    - Lyman, Frederick W., 1844-1856; (7 letters) (Folder 26.3)
    - Maynard, Lucy Piper, 1848-1849; (3 letters) (Folder 26.4)
    - Salmon, George, 1856-1858; (2 letters) (Folder 26.5)
  - Letters to Maria Clara Maynard Salmon
    - Belden, Miranda Smith, 1837-1838; (9 letters) (Folder 26.7)
    - Belden, Miranda Smith, 1839-1841; (9 letters) (Folder 26.8)
    - Belden, Miranda Smith, 1842-1843; (9 letters) (Folder 26.9)
    - Belden, Miranda Smith, 1844-1847; (6 letters) (Folder 26.10)
    - Belden, Pomeroy, 1846-1849; (7 letters) (Folder 26.11)
    - Dickinson, Maria, 1833-1837; (12 letters) (Folder 26.12)
    - Lyman, Frederick W., 1843-1859; (5 letters) (Folder 27.1)
    - Maynard, James B., 1836-1838; (12 letters) (Folder 27.2)
    - Maynard, James B., 1839-1847; (9 letters) (Folder 27.3)
    - Maynard, James B., 1848-1850; (12 letters) (Folder 27.4)
    - Maynard, James B., 1851-1860; (18 letters) (Folder 27.5)
    - Maynard, Louis Capet; See Box 28
    - Maynard, Lucy Piper, 1831-1835; (8 letters, 1 TS) (Folder 27.6)
    - Maynard, Lucy Piper, 1836-1848; (8 letters) (Folder 27.7)
    - Maynard, Sarah McLean, 1857-1860; (6 letters) (Folder 27.8)
    - Salmon, George, 1842-1858; (10 letters) (Folder 27.9)
    - Stone, D.P. (Mrs.), 1840-1849; (9 letters) (Folder 27.10)
    - Whaley, Sophia D., 1846-1861, undated; (9 letters) (Folder 27.11)
    - A-Z Correspondence
    - "Andelusia" – Comstock, 1836-1851; (9 letters) (Folder 28.1)
    - Dole – Freeman, 1818-1859; (14 letters) (Folder 28.2)
    - Gould – Lyon, 1826-1859; (16 letters) (Folder 28.3)
    - Marsh - Mt. Holyoke, 1832-1859, undated; (14 letters) (Folder 28.4)
    - Piper – Rice, 1836-1859; (12 letters) (Folder 28.5)
    - Sands – Stone, 1832-1842, undated; (8 letters) (Folder 28.6)
    - Ward – Wright, 1841-1858, undated; (8 letters) (Folder 28.7)
    - Maynard, Louis Capet, 1825-1834; (6 letters) (Folder 28.8)
    - Bishop - Lyman to Miscellaneous, 1843-1940; (22 letters, 2 carbon copies) (Folder 28.9)
- SERIES X. MISCELLANEOUS FILES
  - Burder, Rev. G. "The Hermit", 1818 (Folder 33.2)
  - 15 notebooks used by Lucy Maynard Salmon (12 used at the University of Michigan) (Box 63)
  - A line-a-day diary, 1899-1901 (Box 63)
  - Bibliography (Box 60)
  - Card File (Box 60)
  - Come to Jesus (Box 63)
  - Gift album (Box 63)
  - Guest book used at 263 Mill Street (Box 63)
  - History and Reunion of Falley Seminary (Box 63)
  - Greeley, Horace, Recollections of a Busy Life (Loomis Latin Prize, Falley Seminary) (Box 63)
  - Items removed from diary (Box 63)
  - Jewelry and badges (Box 60)
  - Johnson's Dictionary (Box 63)
  - Longfellow, Hanging of the Crane (Box 63)
  - Cushing, Luther, Rules of Proceeding and Debate (Box 63)
  - Milton, Areopagiticirca (Box 63)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1832-1933; (27 items) (Folders 31.9 - 31.10)
  - Needlework patterns (Box 63)
  - New Testament (Box 63)
  - Perfume advertisement card (Box 63)
  - Picture of Falley Seminary (Box 64 (Oversize))
  - Postcard albums of Sweden and Norway (Box 65)
  - Pollok, R., The Course of Time (Box 63)
  - Salmon, Lucy Maynard - diplomas and membership certificates (Box 64 (Oversize))
  - Salmon, Lucy Maynard, Historical Material, galley proof (Box 60)
  - Salmon, Maria Clara Maynard - Diploma from Ipswich Female Academy, 1833 (Box 64 (Oversize))
  - Sola, An American Girl (Box 63)
  - The Assembly's Shorter Catechism (Box 63)
  - The Lariat, vol. 5, no. 2, 1925 Feb (Folder 33.1)
  - Woodbridge's School Atlas (1829) and manuscript math test (Box 63)
  - Wooden box with sliding lid (Box 63)
- SERIES XI. POMEROY L. SALMON PAPERS
  - Correspondence
    - Letters to Lucy Maynard Salmon
      - Hubbard, Margaret S. McDougal, 1906 May 2; (1 letter) (Folder 66.01)
      - Salmon, Maynard Hubbard, 1899, 1901; (3 letters) (Folder 66.02)
    - Letters to Maria Clara Maynard Salmon
      - "Lucia", 1850 Feb 6; (1 letter) (Folder 66.03)
      - Unidentified, 1837, 1840, undated; (2 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 66.04)
    - Letters from Maynard Hubbard Salmon
      - "Auntie Mills", 1894 Jun 2; (1 letter) (Folder 66.05)
      - Salmon, Margaret Maynard Hubbard, 1897-1900; (4 letters) (Folder 66.06)
      - Unidentified family members, 1906; (1 letter) (Folder 66.07)
    - Letters to Maynard Hubbard Salmon
      - Hubbard, Margaret S. McDougal, 1906 May 2; (1 letter) (Folder 66.08)
      - Salmon, Lucy Maynard, 1900 Jan 21; (1 letter) (Folder 66.09)
    - Letters from Pomeroy L. Salmon
      - "Cousin Kirt", circa 1855; (1 letter) (Folder 66.10)
      - Salmon, Maria Clara Maynard, 1854-1855; (7 letters) (Folder 66.11)
      - Salmon, Maynard Hubbard, 1901 Aug 10; (1 letter) (Folder 66.12)
    - Letters to Pomeroy L. Salmon
      - Comstock, F. L., 1854-1855; (4 letters) (Folder 66.13)
      - Perkins, Harriet Loomis and Daniel W., 1869, undated; (4 letters) (Folder 66.14)
      - Salmon, Caroline E. Page, 1864-1865, undated; (5 letters) (Folder 66.15)
      - Salmon, George, 1854-1865; (16 letters) (Folder 66.16)
      - Salmon, Helen O., 1900; (2 letters) (Folder 66.17)
      - Salmon, Katherine A. Hathaway, with obituary transcripts, 1900, 1992; (1 letter, 1 MS, 1 TS) (Folder 66.18)
      - Salmon, Lucy Maynard, 1854, 1900; (3 letters) (Folder 66.19)
      - Salmon, Maria Clara Maynard, 1854-1855; (17 letters) (Folder 66.20)
      - Salmon, Maria Clara Maynard, 1865, undated; (5 letters) (Folder 66.21)
      - Salmon, Maynard Hubbard, 1899-1901, undated; (13 letters) (Folder 66.22)
      - Others, 1875-1876, undated; (5 letters, 1 envelope) (Folder 66.23)
    - Letters to and from Others
      - Letter from John Niles Hubbard to [George?] Salmon, 1867 Nov 12; (1 letter) (Folder 66.24)
      - Letters from Margaret S. McDougal Hubbard to Others, 1910-1913; (3 letters) (Folder 66.25)
      - Letters to and concerning Mary Welden, 1899-1907; (8 letters) (Folder 66.26)
      - Unidentified letters, undated; (2 letters) (Folder 66.27)
  - Other Materials
    - Clippings, 1862, undated (Folder 66.28)
    - Cross stitch, "To My Father", undated (Folder 66.29)
    - Drawing of a monument, undated (Folder 66.30)
    - Leaflet - "Description of Bronze Frieze in the Writing Room of The Portland, Portland, Ore.", undated (Folder 66.31)
    - Maynard, M. L. - Essay, "Questions on Chemistry", undated; [1 ms] (Folder 66.32)
    - Notebook with household inventory, undated (Folder 66.33)
    - Notes on family events, post-1943 (Folder 66.34)
    - Pamphlet - Gates, J. C., "Teachers' Assistant and Scholars' Guide…", 1837 (Folder 66.35)
    - Pepper, Julia [?.] - Last Will and Testament, 1870 Nov 12 (Folder 66.36)
    - Salmon, George - Certificate of honorary membership for the American Board of Comissioners for Foreign Missions, 1841 Mar 22 (Folder 66.37)
    - Salmon, George - Certificate of membership in the Oswega County Bible Society, 1849 (Folder 66.38)
    - Salmon, George - Certificates of donation to the construction of the Washington Monument in Washington D.C., undated (Folder 66.39)
    - Salmon, George - Insurance notes, 1865-1866 (Folder 66.40)
    - Salmon, Maria Clara Maynard - Certificate of honorary membership for the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1847 Apr 30 (Folder 66.41)
    - Salmon, Pomeroy L. - Essays, 1863, undated; [6 ms] (Folder 66.42)
    - Salmon, Pomeroy L. - Financial note, 1865 (Folder 66.43)
    - United States bank notes, 1849, 1863; [2 notes] (Folder 66.44)